Marco Ferra

SAFe® 6 Scrum Master (SSM) • Lean Six Sigma Black Belt (LSSBB) • MSc Engineering • EN/PT

Profile

18+ years driving cross-functional delivery and optimising processes across Fortune 500 environments in software, automotive and aerospace. Proven in regulated contexts (AS9100, ISO 9001 roles including Head of Laboratory, CI Lead, and Management Consultant, ISO 17025) and global operations, consistently improving time-to-market, quality, and cost using Agile/Lean Six Sigma. Experience spans Head of Laboratory, CI Lead, and Management Consultant roles. Fluent in English & Portuguese. Based in Lisbon.

ARPA member of the SDF UNIX System. Regular donor and member of the Portuguese committee for UNICEF Portugal.

Professional Career

Programme Manager | Sky - NBCUniversal / Comcast Group, Lisbon, Portugal

Oct 2022 - Present

Accelerated releases by 20% by implementing DORA metrics to expose CI/CD bottlenecks and leading SDLC process
re-engineering across multiple programmes. Scaled Lean-Agile operating metrics (Cycle Time, Throughput) and
ceremonies across 30+ squads to standardise delivery governance and transparency for ~300+ engineers.

Continuous Improvement Lead | Amgen, Lisbon, Portugal

Sep 2021 - Oct 2022

- Established GBS CI strategy and mapped key processes (DMAIC, VSM) to identify and remove bottlenecks.
- Led cross-functional CI initiatives spanning 300+ staff across 3 business units.

Senior Project Manager | Hertz, London, United Kingdom

Jun 2019 - Sep 2021

Enabled €20M+ in annual VAS revenue by leading international projects to improve upsell & cross-sell at online rental
checkout. Advised data-science teams on Lean Six Sigma techniques to boost operational efficiency across models
and processes. Deployed advanced telemetry for mixed fleet in selected European locations to enhance utilisation
and service quality.

Senior Management Consultant | New Angle, Lisbon, Portugal

Mar 2018 - Jun 2019

 Trained & coached 100+ professionals in multinational clients on Lean Six Sigma and Operational Excellence, raising CI capability. Delivered 12% OPEX reduction and 15% throughput increase by designing and implementing lean manufacturing systems for a leading industrial equipment manufacturer.

Head of Electrical Metrology Laboratory | ISQ, Lisbon, Portugal

Jun 2007 – Jun 2019

Built and led a 10+ engineer high-performing team across multiple European locations, instituting robust performance and quality governance. Ran LSSBB programmes that improved operational efficiency and reduced round-trip lead times, delivering >€6M+/year impact. Expanded ISO-17025 accredited services and streamlined lab processes, adding >€1M+/year in revenue potential while passing major audits (ISO-17025, ISO-9001, AS9100).

Education & Certifications

•	Certified SAFe 6 Scrum Master (SSM) Scaled Agile, Inc.	2021
•	Certified Lean Six Sigma Black Belt (LSSBB) University of Lisbon	2017
•	Post-Graduate Certification in Laboratory Management ISQ	2011
•	Certificado de Competências Pedagógicas (CCP) IEFP	2009
•	MSc. Electrical & Computer Engineering Instituto Superior Técnico (University of Lisbon)	2006